<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Future of the Internet | Ozzie Gooen]]></title>
  <link href="http://OAGr.github.io/blog/categories/future-of-the-internet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://OAGr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-16T23:42:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://OAGr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ozzie Gooen]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ozzie.gooen@80000hours.org]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Tell if a Web Company is Evil]]></title>
    <link href="http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/30/how-to-tell-if-a-web-company-is-evil/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/30/how-to-tell-if-a-web-company-is-evil</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m sick of companies cherry picking specific features to explain how they help people.  Specific features will always exist, and the existence of them ruins the point.  The big question is, is it really the purpose of the company to help people, or is helping people an occasional externality of other goals they are trying to achieve?  It’s hard to give someone credit for a positive action that was done for a malicious or unrelated purpose.<br />
<a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/basic.png"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/basic.png?w=590" alt="Altruistic vs. Power Ven Diagram" title="Altruistic vs. Power Ven Diagram" /> </a></p>

<p>Here’s an Altruism/Power Ven Diagram.  On the left are decisions a company makes to help people, on the right are decisions that give them power.  Figuring out the intentions of a company may have little to do with how much they are helping people, because that intersection may be quite large.  The bigger question is how they pay attention to the other parts of the diagram.</p>

<p><a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/people.png"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/people.png?w=300" alt="Optimizing for People" /> </a>  </p>

<p>If a company were optimizing for people, it’s actions may look like this.  </p>

<p><a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/shareholders.png"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/shareholders.png?w=300" alt="If a company optimized for its corporate shareholders, it's actions would be here." /> </a>  </p>

<p>If a company optimized for its corporate shareholders, it’s actions would be here.  </p>

<p>The big question is which of these two above graphs better represents the actions of a company, not how much there is of an intersection to show to the press.  Here’s a graph of what I see as being decisions in each sector, you can decide for yourself what the aims of your favorite web companies may be.  </p>

<p><a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/web-applications.png"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/web-applications.png?w=300" alt="Web Application Altruism/Power Daigram" /> </a><br />
Web Application Altruism/Power Diagram</p>

<h2 id="doesnt-power-eventually-help-users">Doesn’t Power Eventually Help Users?</h2>
<p>This is the main argument from all power grabbers, ever.  That “with more resources, we can do more good,” so decisions to increase power eventually do help users.  While this can be used to justify almost any action, there does exist the fact that without power even the most idealistic or altruistic groups will not succeed.  It also makes sense that those in power will be those optimized to get power over all other things. It may be that most existing companies (organizations, really) only exist to gain power, where the argument is that the power will eventually be (and occasionally is) used for the goals of these organizations (which are supposedly things other than pure shareholder value). But here, how do you identify groups with good intentions from the rest?  From the outside view, they look almost exactly the same, because they are optimizing for power whenever options are presented. It is true that trade-offs need to be made, but for them to be made well there should be some greater model and rigorous attention to the tradeoffs.  Could companies sponsor studies on how to optimize the numeric trade-offs between short term power grabs and long term civilian value?  It may be hard, but given that these organizations sometimes seem to actually care (or want to care) about value to society, it probably wouldn’t cost much compared to other things they are doing. </p>

<h2 id="the-economic-near-ideal">The Economic Near-Ideal</h2>
<p>Of course, one solution would be to create companies where there are few trade-offs.  One can argue that companies like <a href="https://www.10gen.com/">10gen</a> have nice models where they very well align their own power increases with societal benefit.  </p>

<p><a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/ideal.png"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/ideal.png?w=300" alt="The economic near-ideal" /> </a>  </p>

<p>Here companies aren’t defined by how good they are trying to be, but by how much their selfish actions are correlated with altruistic ones.  Here the decision is much more about deciding what kind of company to make (and for outsiders, deciding rules and publicity), then deciding what features to implement.  Yet it also may mean that the more altruistic people will favor industries where this correlation is high, leaving other industries as easy prey for less idealistic people.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Designing the Feedhaven Ecosystem]]></title>
    <link href="http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/30/feedhaven-ecosystem/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/30/feedhaven-ecosystem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/screen-shot-2013-04-29-at-11-02-44-pm.png"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/screen-shot-2013-04-29-at-11-02-44-pm.png?w=922" alt="Feedhaven Diagram 1.0" /> </a>  </p>

<p>We’ve been working a lot recently to figure out what the <a href="http://feedhaven.org/">Feedhaven</a> system should look like.  Right now it’s relatively simple, but to properly work in an ecosystem of applications it would need some additional complexities. </p>

<p><strong>Feedhaven Instances</strong><br />
  In this case a Feedhaven Instance / Server is shown to the right.  A user can set up their own Feedhaven instance, or can use a company’s hosted instance (like <a href="http://feedhaven.com">Feedhaven.com</a>).  This instance is in charge of providing a GUI for the information, storing data on users, handling API keys, and handing the standard Feedhaven data.  This should be able to work on many NoSQL databases, though we plan to begin with MongoDB. </p>

<p><strong>Authentication</strong><br />
  Mozilla Persona seems like a good fit for authentication, especially because it can be standardized among all Feedhaven instances and applications.  Hypothetically Persona could provide proof that an application has confirmation from a user (to send to other applications), but I’m not sure how this would work.  It’s also open source, distributed, easy to set up, and quite minimal.  With Persona integration in the browser, log-in may eventually be a relatively easy thing.  </p>

<p><strong>Data Validation</strong><br />
  Hypothetically all items and feed data would be validated with external JSON schemas with version numbers.  I imagine that for large amounts of data the schemas would have to be cached, and it may be that validation isn’t required, but is possible with an extra function.  </p>

<p><strong>Simple Translation Apps/ Simple Feedhaven Apps</strong><br />
  The idea for this is that users can create API keys with specific permissions at their Feedhaven Instance.  Then this can be given to an external application to allow them to access Feedhaven data without registering with Feedhaven.  Applications that do this would have restricted API call allowances, but this should be fine for many apps.  This is how many major APIs already work; with API tokens for some apps that don’t have to register. These simple apps could do things like read emails from Gmail, convert them to a common email format, and send these to a specific Feedhaven Feed.  They could write or delete specific feeds, and read new common emails from these feeds and then send them off to Gmail.  Whether the app does polling or subscribing to access this content from Feedhaven would be up to the application.  In addition, these apps can be used to just view Feedhaven data. </p>

<p><strong>Translation Manager Apps</strong><br />
  There are hundreds of thousands of applications to talk to, and much of the code to translate each and send/receive to Feedhaven will be the same/similar.  I would imagine/hope that platforms could exist that could accept hundreds or thousands of snippets for conversion with different apps and schemas, and run them as needed. For this, rather than using a standard API token, these apps would have to register directly to each Feedhaven instance.  This should be standardized and done via API calls, when needed. </p>

<p><strong>Future Development</strong><br />
  Of course, the system still needs to be built. The idea is that ecosystem would be fully modular so each part could be built independently based on well defined interfaces.  However, this will take a lot of trial and error as the interfaces are changed based on the workings of the components.  Updates will come at this blog.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Consumer Fishtraps]]></title>
    <link href="http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/28/consumer-fishtraps/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/28/consumer-fishtraps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/121378.jpg"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/121378.jpg?w=487" alt="Image" /> </a></p>

<p>Fishtraps are devices that are easy to enter and difficult or impossible to exit from.  Many products and web apps work the same way. One example may be the <a href="http://www.freecreditreport.com/">monthly service </a>that requires a short website to sign up to but a very long phone call process to stop.  Web services can do similar by making it really simple to sign up and start adding information, but almost impossible to export your data once you use the service. Companies spend a lot of time and effort optimizing their entrences.  There are <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_ss_i_0_14?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;field-keywords=landing%20page%20optimization&amp;sprefix=landing+page+o%2Caps%2C213&amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Alanding%20page%20optimization">several books</a> on Landing Page Optimization / SEO / AB testing on acquiring users.  There’s basically nothing on how to allow users to gracefully leave. Easy web exiting capabilities for consumers would mean data (and permissions and API) interoperability which would mean open standards.  This is one big reason why open standards are important.  But open web standards over the last 10 years have been very rough and frustrating, much because of a reluctance of companies to allow their users to easily leave their platforms.   </p>

<h2 id="the-facebook-example">The Facebook Example</h2>
<p>To start using Facebook, there’s one clean landing page.  Once you get in, Facebook will give you lots of help finding friends for you.  They will then recommend you to people who “might” know you, to help make sure that you get comfortable quickly.  The entire process is incredibly simple and easy. But say you get tired of Facebook, and want to try Google+.  You can close your Facebook account, but they will keep the information forever (allowing you to re-enter as easily as possible).  If you search through the option settings, you may find that on the bottom of the “general account settings” page, there’s a way to “download a copy” of your Facebook data.  This brings you to another page, as shown below.</p>

<p><a href="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/screen-shot-2013-04-28-at-3-38-55-pm.png"> <img src="http://bowlabs.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/screen-shot-2013-04-28-at-3-38-55-pm.png" alt="Facebook Archive Page" /> </a></p>

<p>If you click “Start My Archive”, you actually won’t get that much data.  The full archive link is actually that small “expanded archive” link on the bottom.  From there you enter your password and wait. Several hours later you’ll get an email letting you know your archive is ready.  It comes as a folder with several HTML webpages of your pictures, friends, private messages, and profile information.  Not CSV, not JSON, but HTML data. Then you realize that even that doesn’t have the status updates of you or your friends.  I don’t know how many people use Facebook primarily as a photo sharing service, but I’m going to go on a limb and say that the main thing people do on Facebook is post to and read from status updates.  So Facebook is essentially not giving the most important user data to them. And even then, there’s really no way I know of importing any of that data to Google+ or Twitter or Diaspora.  Because in order to do that, these programs would have to make a program that you would download, just to format this HTML and then upload it to another service. The saddest part is that even this is considered <strong>better than average</strong> for web services.</p>

<h2 id="solutions">Solutions</h2>
<p>The only existing protection against this seem to be the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Data_Protection_Regulation">EU’s legal action</a> and occasionally consumer sentiment. Hypothetically, it could be possible for a browser extension to warn users about lock-in on visits to website sign-up pages.  If enough people used these or did some research, it could be possible that companies would take notice and respond accordingly.  We really just need people to care. In the mean time, just realize.  When you are on these platforms, you are essentially in a fish trap.  Leaving may technically be feasible, but it’s made to be near impossible.   For more info on “evil web design” I recommend checking out “ <a href="http://ofps.oreilly.com/titles/9781118422144/index.html">Evil By Design</a>” by Chriss Nodder.The <a href="http://ofps.oreilly.com/titles/9781118422144/sloth.html">Sloth section</a> goes into detail in what I am calling the fishtrap.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Information Availability Graph]]></title>
    <link href="http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/27/an-information-availability-graph/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/04/27/an-information-availability-graph</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I’ve been thinking about the economics of sharing person information.   I get the sense that one reason why social networks are so important is because they allow you to share much more information than you would be otherwise.  In general, people seem to think that this a good thing, and I think that these following diagrams may help explain why.   By looking at information sharing in an economic way it may be easier to understand the existing inefficiencies of the “market” and some theoretical reasons for the emergence of social networks and group privacy settings within them.  </p>

<p><a href="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/1.png"> <img src="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/1.png" alt="A person has the most information about themselves available (typically). A much smaller subset of information is available to the public." /> </a>  </p>

<p>A person has the most information about themselves available (typically). A much smaller subset of information is available to the public.</p>

<p>First, I’ll start with the basic plot.  Imagine that you ordered everyone in the world by how willing you were to share information with them, and then plotted how much you would be willing to share with each person.  You would be all the way on the left, deserving of accessing everything.  Then all the way on the right is the general public.  You may share a few pictures of yourself and an email address, but many people choose to hide a lot of information from everybody.  </p>

<p><a href="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/comfortcurve.png"> <img src="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/comfortcurve.png" alt="The Comfort Curve shows the maximum amount of information that a person would feel comfortable sharing with X amount of people. The &quot;optimal&quot; setting would be for this to be completely filled with information." /> </a> </p>

<p>The Comfort Curve shows the maximum amount of information that a person would feel comfortable sharing with X amount of people. The “optimal” setting would be for this to be completely filled with information.  </p>

<p>The result of your ordering and plotting may be a “comfort curve”, which shows exactly how much information availability you would be comfortable with.  We can generally assume that this is what is optimal for the world, given the constraint of you being OK with it.  You being OK is particularly important because that is what you may be willing to share.  Theoretically we could make a model showing how much information should be available for a utilitarian scenario instead, but that would be much more complicated and not as relevant.  </p>

<p><a href="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/facebook.png"> <img src="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/facebook.png" alt="Different platforms allow different groups to access different amounts of your data." /> </a>  </p>

<p>Different platforms allow different groups to access different amounts of your data.  </p>

<p>The privacy of Facebook (and other social networking tools) allow them to promote sharing that would not go on websites.  This privacy enables more people to gain information (that you are fine with them getting) than would be otherwise.  </p>

<p><a href="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/facebook-groups.png"> <img src="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/facebook-groups.png" alt="Facebook added the concept of &quot;types&quot; of friends to help promote sharing. More information availability is possible with more groups to share with." /> </a>  </p>

<p>Facebook added the concept of “types” of friends to help promote sharing. More information availability is possible with more groups to share with.  </p>

<p>One thing a lot of people noticed was that as Facebook became more popular, people became less comfortable sharing on it.  Facebook originally went from being a tool for college friends to one of general acquaintances and colleagues.  Later Facebook allowed users to split their friends up into groups and share with each group separately, to help mitigate this.  Other social networks (Diaspora, Google+) have done this first (and arguably better).  </p>

<p><a href="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/group.png"> <img src="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/group.png" alt="The limitation of groups and mediums limits the information that can become available." /> </a>  </p>

<p>The limitation of groups and mediums limits the information that can become available.  </p>

<p>However, unless you have n groups for n friends, there’s always going to be some information you won’t share to some people because of the limitation of group number.  This “inefficiency” is shown in red.  </p>

<p><a href="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/convencience.png"> <img src="http://raiseforgoodapp.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/convencience.png" alt="The ability and convenience to share information to specific groups also limits information availability, as shown." /> </a>   </p>

<p>The ability and convenience to share information to specific groups also limits information availability, as shown.  </p>

<p>In addition, other information is either be inconvenient or impossible to share.  You probably don’t have access to a lot of information that exists and is about you.  You probably don’t share near all of the information with your facebook friends that you would feel comfortable with them having, because the cost of putting much of it on Facebook far exceeds the benefits that your friends would get from it.  For example, you may not mind at all if your close friends could get info on your GPS location most of the time, or what book you are currently reading, but it may be difficult/inconvenient to push that data to Facebook.  </p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, I think this may present an interesting model from which to build on.  It would be very interesting to make this quantitative, but realize that it would be very complicated.  Similar models could be made for businesses, organizations, etc.  This also doesn’t discuss what other people want to see; only what you are willing to show them. One of my goals with Feedhaven is to minimize both of these inefficiencies. Hypothetically, all of the information available to you (no matter the app) could have one generalized retrieval system.  In addition, one could imagine systems whereby it were incredibly simple and elegant to split up friends into tiny groups and to edit settings for each one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bringing all things down to Wikipedia's level]]></title>
    <link href="http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/03/13/bringing-all-things-down-to-wikipedias-level/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://OAGr.github.io/blog/2013/03/13/bringing-all-things-down-to-wikipedias-level</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/posts/wikipedia.png" alt="wikipedia" />
You’ve probably heard of several stories of people posting false information on Wikipedia.  It seems to be the number one type of story I hear about Wikipedia.  And these stories are used to explain why we shouldn’t be allowed to site Wikipedia or pay much attention to it as our primary source of knowledge.  </p>

<p>The trouble with this thinking is that most people seem to pay less attention to the stories of poor academic writing, or news articles, or just about every other thing written in any language ever.  </p>

<p>Wikipedia acknowledges that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:General_disclaimer"> it has problems with accuracy</a>.  Most other groups have similar problems, but many won’t say so, for obvious reasons. </p>

<p>My main fear is that universities and organizations ban Wikipedia references as a way to feign truth where little exists.  The stark reality, from my perspective, is that the vast majority of information all of us see is misrepresented, incomplete, false, and irrelevant.  People, journalists, scientists, often tell stories instead of facts, and even the facts are carefully chosen (though not always intentionally).  Bias is absolutely everywhere and so far Wikipedia seems to be the best item, to my knowledge, to try to counter it.  It’s a tiny attempt in comparison to the size of the problem, but it seems unfortunate to pin it as the enemy. </p>

<p><strong>I think that people like to use Wikipedia as a scapegoat and shove it under a bus.  But the problem isn’t Wikipedia, the problem is the inherently biased nature of humanity and lack of care or infrastructure to address this.</strong> </p>

<p>So I agree that Wikipedia is uncertain.  But it’s probably much better than what’s in my head currently about almost everything ever.  I think we need to just admit that most of what we know is very flawed and accept that all communicated and known information is imperfect, because it is.  Incredibly so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
